<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ground of a Christians life Deliuered in a sermon at Harwood in Lancashire, the first day of December 1618. By Robert Worthington minister of Gods word at Acceington.</title>
            <author>Worthington, Robert, minister of Gods word at Acceington.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103650</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839399</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3815</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3815)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1264:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ground of a Christians life Deliuered in a sermon at Harwood in Lancashire, the first day of December 1618. By Robert Worthington minister of Gods word at Acceington.</title>
                  <author>Worthington, Robert, minister of Gods word at Acceington.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Field for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at the great south doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Gods word the safest guide.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GROVND OF A CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIANS LIFE. Deliuered in a Sermon at Harwood in Lancaſhire, the firſt day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 1618.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ROBERT WORTHINGTON <hi>Miniſter of Gods word at Acceington.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Heb. 11. 6.</bibl>
            <q>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</q>
            <bibl>Iohn 6. 68.</bibl>
            <q>Lord to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of eternall life.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Field</hi> for <hi>Robert Mylbourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at the great South doore of Paules. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle propheſied that in<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 5. 2. Tim. 4. 3.</note> the laſt dayes ſhold come perillous times, when men hauing a ſhew of godlineſſe ſhould denie the power therof: &amp; refuſing wholſome dostrine, through their itching eares, ſhould get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues an heape of teachers. What proud Anabaptiſt, that vaunteth himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſtage of vaine Imagination, or ſecure Papiſt, that truſteth to the broken ſtaffe of Egypt, can free himſelfe from ſuch ſpirituall maladies? who leauing the key of knowledge, and fountaines of liuing water, haue digged vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:3815:3"/> broken ciſternes. And no maruell: ſince Satan cantransforme himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11. 14.</note> an Angell of light, how can he worke in the darkened vnderſtanding, and the heart not truly humbled? He that dare enter combat with the Lord of glorie, wiſdome and ſoueraigntie, and offer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the full and onely point of mans redemption; how boldly will this politicke and puiſſant enemie inuade Gods Church, wraſtling with vs about that ſtaffe of faith whereby we ſtand, &amp; ſeeke to ſtrip vs of that ſhield which is<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 16.</note> able to keepe backe all his fierie darts? What ſoldier is there in Chriſts campe, if he do but watch, that ſhall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his ſubtill enterpriſes? Chriſts watchword was not in vaine, <hi>Watch &amp; pray, leſt ye enter into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 26. 41.</note> nor his prayer needleſſe for his ſeruant Peter, <hi>I haue prayed for thee,<note place="margin">Luk, 22. 32.</note> that thy faith faile not.</hi> For what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter treacherie then to ſtrike at the root? (witneſſed in the Gunpowder treaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:3815:3"/> hatched by Satan and his inſtruments,) or what greater follie, then to build an houſe without a foundation? To this purpoſe is my weake &amp; vnperfect labor at this time, the which I had thought to haue ſhrowded vnder ſome Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, but conſidering with my ſelfe, I thought ſo ſmall a worke deſerued not a patronage of anie worth: and the rather therefore haue I ſent it to the broade world to ſeeke for it ſelfe, truſting that there is no faithfull heart that will denie ſo plaine and needfull a doctrine enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. Yet I feare that if it ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meete with Atheiſt, Anabaptiſt, Papiſt, or earthly worldling, it is like (without Gods mercie) to finde as litle friendſhip as Chriſt the author of faith did among the Gadarens. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">Math 8. 34.</note> I haue at the earneſt deſires of ſome, as alſo for the defence of my ſelfe, if haply anie popiſh ſurmiſer or other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret opinioniſt ſhould ariſe in oppoſition (it being preached in a countrey where
<pb facs="tcp:3815:4"/> are many aduerſaries of our faith) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to commit that to publike view which before I deliuered in open aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, not aduenturing to change my ſtyle, leſt I ſhould bewray my ſelfe of follie, in bringing vnto light a groundleſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: it being like to be peruſed by ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower iudgements then manie of thoſe who were preſent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was at the firſt diuulged. Wherfore I beſeech thee (gentle Reader) that if by Gods bleſſing thou ſhalt gaine to thy ſelfe hereby, either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of thy iudgement, or confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudgement, or thy will proucked to a more conſtant vigilancie ouer thy wayes, remember to returne to him that rent of thankfulneſſe vnto whom thou art bound, from whom thou receiueſt euery good and perfest gift: praying withall for the vnitie of Gods Church, the propagation of the Goſpell, that through the meanes of grace, in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and out of ſeaſon, thy faith being ſtrengthened, when this life of faith
<pb facs="tcp:3815:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall be finiſhed, Chriſt the obiect of thy faith may aſſigne thee the end of thy faith, ſeating thee in his celestiall Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem with true beleeuers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, Robert Worthington.</signed> 
               <dateline>Acceington.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3815:5"/>
            <head>The ground of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians life, deliuered in a <hi>Sermon at Harwood the first</hi> day of September. 1618.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. 14. 23.</bibl>
               <q>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bleſſed Apoſtle in the<note place="margin">The cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Text.</note> eight verſe of the former Chapter, exhorteth vnto that royall law of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being that new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<note place="margin">Loue a grace of abſolute neceſſitie in Gods church Iohn 13. 34.</note> propounded by his Lord and Sauiour, as a grace ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to be in Gods Church: <hi>A new commandement</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>giue I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that ye loue one another: as I haue loued you, that you alſo loue one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now inuiſible graces muſt haue viſible teſtimonies, both for the manifeſtation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3815:6"/> of the graces themſelues, as alſo for our iuſtification before men; therefore in this chapter the Apoſtle taketh occaſion to deſcribe and teach the proper effect of this Chriſtian grace, it being of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as to edifie and ſupport, according to his owne teſtimonie, <hi>Loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 1. 1. Cor. 14. 26.</note> his generall command is, <hi>Let all things be done to edifying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were in this church, ſome ſtrong,<note place="margin">Sound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vp of Gods church.</note> others weake; as there ſhalbe euer poore in the world, that the rich may exerciſe their pity and compaſſion, ſo weake in the Church, that the ſtrong may exerciſe their loue and affection, to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues hereby faithfull diſpoſers and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſers of the manifold g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of God. Chriſt was the nurſing father of his little flocke: neuer was it knowne that he<note place="margin">Eſay 42. 3.</note> broke the bruiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed, or quenched the ſmoaking flaxe; ſo muſt Chriſtians, whoſe Image they beare, and whom they are to follow, daily exerciſe this grace of loue, ſince God hath giuen to euery one the meaſure of faith.</p>
            <p>Hard was it to bring this people from the traditions of their fathers, or to wean them from the law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ceremonies, <hi>Touch</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 21.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3815:6"/> 
               <hi>not, taſte not, handle not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Apoſtle dealeth with them as new borne babes, putting a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference<note place="margin">Corruption not eaſly wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie.</note> betweene them and the ſtrong. Some had receiued the full power of Chriſtian liberty, others had not attained vnto it: but were like punies in their A, B, C, not fully ſatisfied in this poynt, that <hi>vnto the pure all things were pure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now the drift of the Apoſtle is to ſchoole the ſtrong, and teach the weake, not ruinating, but nouriſhing the worke of God which was in both; ſhewing the neceſſitie of faith and loue in the Church of God: for, as he correcteth the one for<note place="margin">The correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſinne muſt be the erecting of grace.</note> putting a ſtumbling blocke before the weake in things indifferent, ſo he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the other to be fully perſwaded in his mind. <hi>For he that doubteth, is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if he eate,</hi> that is, <hi>is guiltie of impietie before God;</hi> which is expounded in the words following, becauſe <hi>he eateth not of faith.</hi> To conclude by an Antitheſis in my Text, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi> Where there is not faith, there muſt<note place="margin">A wicked cauſe brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth a bad effect.</note> needes be doubting, and where is doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there is ſinne: a miſerable cauſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily produceth a lamentable effect,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3815:7"/> for ſo much is verified in this concluſion: <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words are three things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable.<note place="margin">The diuiſion.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>1 The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie,</head>
               <item>Whatſoeuer, that is, anie actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though not indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; wherin is included thoghts, words, works.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>2 The cauſe,</head>
               <item>Not of faith, that is, not aſſured in conſcience v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſound ground.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>3 The effect,</head>
               <item>Is ſinne, that is, impietie a breach of the Law of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It is not ſaid, That which is againſt<note place="margin">The opening of the Text.</note> faith, but that action which is without faith diſpleaſeth God, whether greater or leſſer matters, either things abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary; or caſually indifferent. Now<note place="margin">There may be a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence where there is no faith. 1. Cor. 10. 29.</note> ſome take faith for the conſcience, which cannot be; for the weake may haue a conſcience when they haue not faith, as witneſſeth the Apoſtle himſelfe: <hi>And the conſcience, I ſay not thine, but of that other;</hi> meaning the weake. <hi>For why ſhould my liberty be condemned of another mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> Secondly, errour is not faith; but the conſcience is oftentimes erronious:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3815:7"/> therefore the faith of hereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes is no faith, but rather credulitie, yet they haue a conſcience.</p>
            <p>Neither is euery opinion &amp; perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mind and conſcience, faith, but that which is grounded vpon the word. So then, faith is a ſound perſwaſion of<note place="margin">Fides dicitur firma animi certitudo quae ex Dei veritate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta ſit, à qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſi minimum deflectit non iam fides, ſed incerta eſt credulitas &amp; vagus mentis error. Caluin. in lib. Inſtit. cap. 5. <hi>The maine doctrine from the full ſcope of the Text.</hi>
               </note> the mind, conceiued from Gods truth; &amp; the man that would do an acceptable worke with the Lord, muſt worke it of faith, that is, as I haue partly ſaid, an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in conſcience grounded vpon the word, that it may be done or not be done. For ſuch things as are required in the Scriptures, are pleaſing vnto him; wherefore, where the word of God is not, there is no faith.</p>
            <p>The doctrine then to be examined and extracted from hence, is this, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is done without knowledge and perſwaſion from the tenor of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be truth to them that do it, that action is a ſinne. Many haue aduentured from their variable opinions and vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conceits to draw peremptorie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, and theſe in themſelues haue carried a golden gloſſe, and appeared as Criſtall: but when they haue beene laid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3815:8"/> to the touchſtone of Gods ſacred truth for further triall, they were found to be but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> beautifull deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yea meere fallacies, not any whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable to pacifie the minde, or giue full and ſound ſatisfaction to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>In what high eſteeme and reputation<note place="margin">Humane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and carnall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination not a ſufficient guide in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual affaires.</note> among the people were the Phariſees phylacteries, and what gliſtering ſhewes of an vnblameable profeſſion did they make? But when the day-ſtarre aroſe, and he who was brighter then the Sunne appeared, their glorious profeſſion is but like an houſe without a foundation, yea, as vaine as <hi>Agrippaes</hi> pompe, or <hi>Herods</hi> apparrell. Chriſt with his owne mouth giueth teſtimony of their folly, telling them in plaine ſpeeches, that <hi>That which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16. 15.</note> 
               <hi>is highly eſteemed of among men, is an abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay further, what good intentions, as they are called, yet how naked with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their garment of faith, how ſlipperie for want of a ſtay, taxed by our Sauiour, and reproued in the diſciples themſelues? <hi>Peter, put vp thy ſword into his place:</hi> As if<note place="margin">Matth. 26. 52.</note> he ſhould ſay, Thy intent is good, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3815:8"/> thou wanteſt a ground, for I muſt ſuffer. How could I be deliuered into the hands of the Iewes, but that the Scriptures<note place="margin">Verſe 54.</note> muſt be fulfilled, which ſay it muſt be ſo? I haue a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for my ſuffering, but thou haſt none for thy ſtriking: <hi>Peter</hi> therfore put vp thy ſword, for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> likewiſe are very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory<note place="margin">Luke 9. 54.</note> for want of entertainement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Samaritans, but Chriſt tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them of a prepoſterous zeale, and an vnwarrantable aſſertion. For he came to be a Sauiour, and not a deſtroyer: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at this time they want a ground for their raſh purpoſes and indiſcreete de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, though otherwiſe they make neuer ſo goodly a ſhew in zeale and intention.<note place="margin">Num. 15. 32.</note> Furthermore, <hi>the man that gathered ſtickes vpon the Sabbath;</hi> and <hi>Vzzah that put</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 6. 7. Bare intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cannot be the ground of a ſound faith.</note> 
               <hi>foorth his hand to ſtay the Arke of God,</hi> the open ſhaking it cannot be thought to want good intentions for that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed; yet becauſe they went againſt the great command of that high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, his direfull hand of iuſtice irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocably ſubuerteth them; for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3815:9"/>
            <p>The reaſons follow Firſt, becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> action is not can be good or acceptable, as witneſſeth the Authour to the Hebrewes, <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>to pleaſe God.</hi> If God accept any worke, it is through Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which worke there is required, not onely the doing, but the well doing, vnto the which there is needfull, ſound ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, a right maner, and a good end, the Lord Ieſus himſelfe being not onely adiutor, but alſo a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to his Church. The materiall taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle muſt be framed, and faſhioned, and<note place="margin">Exod. 25. 9.</note> furniſhed according to the Lords owne direction: there muſt likewiſe be neither addition nor abſtraction from thoſe ten words deliuered in the Mount, as it is written in Deuteronomy, <hi>Take heed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut 5. 32.</note> 
               <hi>that you do as the Lord your God hath commanded you, turne not aſide neither to the right hand nor to the left.</hi> The Iew and Papiſt they worſhip the true God, but<note place="margin">Wil-worſhips were euer ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable before the Lord.</note> not according to that manner the Lord requireth: therefore their ſeruices are not of faith: and if not of faith, not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Chriſt and his Father are one, ſo are their lawes; therefore whatſoeuer we ask the Father in his name, he heareth vs.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3815:9"/> Yea (ſaith the Apoſtle) whatſoeuer we aske, <hi>we receiue of him, becauſe we keepe his</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3. 22.</note> 
               <hi>commandements, and do thoſe things which are pleaſing in his ſight:</hi> but <hi>without faith we cannot pleaſe God,</hi> therefore without faith there can be no acceptance: for <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> My ſecond reaſon is taken from the infallibilitie and truth of Scriptures. We haue (ſaith the Apoſtle) a moſt true word of the Prophets; which may appeare, firſt from the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r: For no propheſie in Scriptures is of any priuate motion, but<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 20. verſe 21.</note> 
               <hi>holy men of God ſpake as they were moued by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Looke we at <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and we ſhall finde their tongues to be<note place="margin">Eſay 6. 7. Scriptures without er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> touched with <hi>coles from Gods Altar,</hi> and the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> to be doubled vpon <hi>Eliſha;</hi> yea they were <hi>all filled with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, and ſpake as the Spirit gaue them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>vtterance.</hi> What words of groſſe impiety, or rather blaſphemy, dare the Papiſts vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, concluding theſe ſacred writings, without the authoritie of the Church as not authenticall? Yea they authorize Canons to be as orthodoxal as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. O palpable blindneſſe, nay, horrible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3815:10"/> blaſphemy! But let vs proceed. As the truth of Scripture appeareth by the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo alſo by the matter it ſelfe there in<note place="margin">The pure word of God ſurpaſſeth all humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. That which man by his wiſedome cannot do, God by his word and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit can do.</note> contained. How doth it diſcouer ſinfull mans particular thoughts, luſts &amp; affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which humane reaſon was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcerne, nor any Philoſopher by humane wiſedome able to declare? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what articles of faith, although not againſt reaſon, yet aboue reaſon? For in naturall vnderſtanding God is not all iuſtice and no mercie, but if there were not a Redeemer it ſhould be ſo: therfore, although reaſon can teach, that he muſt be God that muſt ſatisfie the infinite iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God for ſinne, yet that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer ſhould be God and man, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue reaſon. For this cauſe is his name called <hi>Wonderfull.</hi> Vnſpeakeable was the<note place="margin">Eſay 9. 6.</note> worke of creation, and wonderfull the worke of redemption: <hi>This is the Lords</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118 23.</note> 
               <hi>doing though it be maruellous in our eyes:</hi> and, <hi>Let him that glorieth glorie in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Lord.</hi> Beſides, nothing but this word is able to miniſter comfort and reliefe in all diſtreſſes of body and minde. The ſweet promiſes of the Goſpell will onely reuiue and raiſe vp the wearie ſoule, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3815:10"/> giue it ful contentment and ſatisfaction. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> concludeth more perfection<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Athanaſ. de Synod.</hi>
               </note> to be in the Scriptures then all the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods: he therefore that beleeueth God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt beleeue the Scriptures, <hi>for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> The third reaſon is taken from the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Tim. 3. 15.</hi>
               </note> of them, they being able to make a man wiſe to ſaluation, through the faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus. But, ſaith the Aduerſary, they are imperfect, therefore they require a ſupply from the Apoſtolicall Decre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alls of the Church. O proude Babel that dare offer ſtrength to him who is ſtrength and ſufficiencie it ſelfe, and prop his omnipotent power and incomparable worke with the reeds of Aegypt! <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, that the Scriptures<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scriptura co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarium bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum documen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum. Baſil. mag. in pſal. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Iren. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Theod. dial. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap.</hi> 6.</note> are the rich treaſury of the King of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, full of pearles and precious ſtones, wherein the Chriſtian may furniſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with neceſſaries, either for his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral or particular calling. Yea, how haue the ancient Fathers, <hi>Tertullian, Irenaeus, Theodoret, Auguſtine,</hi> made them their ſtay, confeſſing them to be the vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ground of faith, the pillar of truth? How haue they commended them by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3815:11"/> their example &amp; doctrine to all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, as ſufficient to make the man of God abſolutely perfect vnto euerie good worke? Nay further, how haue they expreſly publiſhed vnto poſterities,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieronym in Mat.</hi> 23</note> 
               <hi>Quod de Scripturis authoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non habet, eadem facilitate contemnitur qua probatur,</hi> that is, Whatſoeuer is not authoriſed by the holy Scriptures, it may as eaſily be reiected as receiued. Wherfore, although ſuch Babyloniſh and Satanicall ſpirits, in their height of pride dare atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that which the ſtrength of Iſrael by his owne finger hath ſo confirmed and eſtabliſhed to be both perfect and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 7.</note> yet let all that feare the Lord, conclude with my Text, that <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> My fourth reaſon is taken from the preſent and future expectation of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and comfort through faith in the promiſe, from the worke truly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely<note place="margin">Faith onely the ground of ſound aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance and comfort.</note> wrought, the which cannot be truly and conſtantly expected of me, without full aſſurance in my ſoule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſcience, that I haue throughly ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to obey God in all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will; being truly humbled at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3815:11"/> the ſight of my manifold failings and imperfections. For euangelical perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſteth in theſe graces, faith, vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned humiliation, with an earneſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, God in his Sonne accepting the truth of our endeuours as perfect works. The which euidently appeareth by the teſtimony of the Apoſtle, who although he delighted in the law of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the inner man, yet was he conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to cry in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, <hi>O wretched man that I am!</hi> Were our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions<note place="margin">Rom. 7. 22. 23 24</note> perfect, what neceſſitie were there either of humiliation or faith? but Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall righteouſneſſe requireth both, humiliation to bring vs to faith, &amp; faith for the apprehending of that imputed righteouſneſſe which is by Chriſt. Hence then is diſcloſed the naturall eſtate of many, who bragge of an endeuour to ſerue God, but wanting the cleare ſight<note place="margin">No diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, no endeuouring after perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</note> of imperfections in their beſt actions, they come not to the grace of ſound hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and ſo remaine careleſſe, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the meanes of grace, as conſtant hearing, praying, conferring, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whereby more knowledge, and greater ſtrength is to be obtained; they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3815:12"/> being ignorant of an vniuerſall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed obedience enioyned the people of God. Since therefore his will muſt be our will, and his word an abſolute rule for the ſquaring and ordering of our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall affaires, in the courſes of true pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vnmixed holineſſe: how fraile<note place="margin">Hope with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out faith but a vaniſhing ſhadow.</note> and comfortleſſe is that vaniſhing hope, which is not ſupported with this ſtaffe of Faith? What comelineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were it to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the daughter before the mother, but that groundleſſe actions muſt needes end in fading vanities, &amp; ſeeming ſhewes in baſe hypocriſie? Now the Scriptures tell vs, that we are ſaued by faith, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this grace belongeth the promiſes; for that grace which bringeth vs Chriſt, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs all things: what then can ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 32.</note> be expected without the life of Faith? <hi>Dauid</hi> therefore firſt layeth the ground, and then applieth: <hi>I ſhall not be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 9.</note> 
               <hi>when I haue respect, vnto all thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> gaineth his aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and triumpheth in his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from this vnmoueable ground, <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>I haue kept the faith; from henceforth is laid vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe:</hi> He
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3815:12"/> therefore that will be fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from the guilt of ſin, and enioy the promiſes, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, without wauering, practiſe the workes of faith, for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> Fiftly and laſtly, the example of the Lords Worthies confirme the truth of our propoſed doctrine. <hi>Abraham</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note place="margin">Geneſ. 17. 1. Geneſ 5. 24. Geneſ. 6. 9. Acts 13. 22. Ioſh. 1. 2.</note> before God, <hi>Henoch</hi> with God, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> by Gods owne teſtimony, was an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, <hi>Moſes</hi> was his ſeruant, <hi>Dauid</hi> a man after his owne heart; how could this be, but that by faith they obeyed ſincerely the word of faith? Hence the Apoſtle dare affirme, that As many as<note place="margin">Galat. 6. 16.</note> walke according to this rule, peace ſhall be vpon them and mercy. Therefore, without all controuerſie it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that there can be no ſound life but the life of faith: for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I truſt, by this time, eaſie paſſage is made for further proſecution of the point: proceede we therefore briefly to application.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> In the firſt place therefore it giueth vs to vnderſtand, that he muſt be more then a naturall man, that groundeth his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3815:13"/> ordinarily vpon the word, for the naturall man perceiueth not the things<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 14.</note> of the Spirit of God, neither can he know them: the Apoſtle giueth two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the one taken from his owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, They are fooliſhnes vnto him; the other from the excellencie of the thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelues, the which vnſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied nature cannot be capable of: for as they are ſpirituall, ſo they muſt be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcerned. The vnregenerate man<note place="margin">The life of faith not wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the gifts of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely.</note> may be enriched with many and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gifts, as knowledge, approbation of the beſt things, yea with inclination to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſincerity. What a gliſtering ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue image of holineſſe may the natural man be couered with? how pregnant in diuine and humane hiſtories? He may be ſtored with varietie of the greateſt gifts that Nature can afford him, and expreſſe in action <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> morall vertues, yet neuer come to be ruled vniuerſally by the word, but as a bondſlaue guided and ruled by his enlightened and checking conſcience. <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſell was<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 23.</note> like as one had asked counſell at the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of God: yet was he without diuine and ſupernaturall illumination and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3815:13"/> graces of the Spirit. So it is that many can ſpeake of God, but not in that<note place="margin">Euery ſeruice of god diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth manner as well as matter.</note> holy manner as of God, with reuerence and feare. Others can talke of the word, Sabboth and Saints, but without humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, delight, affection; that as good meate may be marred in the making, ſo good words in ſpeaking: for Gods word directeth, not onely for matter but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>If any man ſpeake</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>let him ſpeake as the words of God.</hi> And. <hi>Paul</hi> commendeth the Theſſalonians for receiuing the Goſpell, not as it was <hi>the word of man,</hi> but as it was indeede, <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>word of God.</hi> Hence it is that the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man feareth to vndertake any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or worſhip due vnto his God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an exact preparation: that is, he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneth his whole fabricke, euery facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſoule and body; inſomuch that he ſaith with <hi>Cornelius, We are all here in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10. 33.</note> 
               <hi>the preſence of God.</hi> He leaueth not vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined his faith and loue, committing a ſeuerall office to his ſeuerall faculties; leſt his ſacrifice ſhould ſmell vnſauourie in the noſtrils of the Almightie, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">Eſay 66. 3.</note> reſpected then the cutting off of a dogges necke, or the offering vp of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3815:14"/> ſwines bloud. He forgetteth not that ſpirituall actions muſt be done in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall manner, leſt that wofull propheſie be verified in him, as it was in the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>This people come neare vnto me with</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 15. 8.</note> 
               <hi>their lippes, but their hearts are farre from me.</hi> Thus, although the carnall Ciuiliſt dare ruſh into Gods ordinances and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeruices, as the horſe into the battell, neuer reſpecting like the careleſſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, how his maiſters worke be done, ſo it be done: yet the tender affected ſonne of Adoption, ſanctified with the graces of Gods Spirit, remembreth and regiſtreth that grounded watch-word, <hi>Take heede to thy foote,</hi> that is, Examine<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. 17.</note> thy thoughts and affections, for, <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is required in diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, although not in humane learning, as philoſophie, that not onely our actions<note place="margin">Gods word, mans heart, and his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize.</note> muſt agree with our mindes, but our minds muſt agree with the truth it ſelfe: for it is not enough that a man walke before God, but that he walke truly and vprightly with his God. For this cauſe hath our gracious God granted and vouchſafed his Pillar of a Cloud, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3815:14"/> his Pillar of fire for our certaine guiding in the way of happineſſe. What better and ſurer conducts can we haue then his Word and Spirit? for what reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do, faith can do. Wherefore in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt be a double truth, truth in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; matter; the one to manifeſt gods truth; the other our owne. Graceleſſe men may ſpeake as they thinke: their words manifeſting the abundance of their hearts; but naturall men can neuer ſpeake Gods truth truly. What grounds then hath imaginary ſuppoſition in the ſeruice of God, or that doctrine of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocation and mentall reſeruation hatcht in the Romiſh Synagogue, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non etenim falſum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rare peierare est: ſed quod ex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi tui ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia iuraue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Cic. de of fic. libr.</hi> 3.</note> of the very heathens? Periury (ſaith one) is not ſo much ſwearing a thing falſe, as ſwearing it falſely, when heart and words agree not. But the parti-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Papiſt may haue out of his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke, a tongue for the Prince, and an heart for the Pope. But let all which ſet their faces towards Sion, know, that without knowledge the minde is not<note place="margin">Prou. 19. 2.</note> good; and that truth is required, not onely in the doer, but alſo in the worke it ſelfe, farre ſurpaſſing the choiſeſt gifts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3815:15"/> of nature, for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, the ſecure Naturaliſt that can ſhew his gilded Armes painted with the colour of ciuil honeſtie, and the formall hypocrite that is ſoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vp to an high pitch of confuſed holineſſe: theſe and<note place="margin">The life of faith excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and formalitie.</note> ſuch like haue framed a repentance of their owne, not grounded vpon the Scriptures. Many take ſome paines in the outward performance of religious duties, &amp; can concurre with Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter in the ſtrict cenſures of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſinnes; yet examine them thorowly in the ground of regeneration, I feare, in reſpect of true and liuely experience, they will be found as ignorant as <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus,</hi> yea as vaine as <hi>Demas:</hi> ſound mortification will be held martyrdome with their carnall affections, whence proceedeth wearineſſe, dulneſſe, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea fearefull backeſliding, the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mother of ſcandall to the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. Nay they liue in the boſome of the Church, yet miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly blinde and naked, deſtitute of thoſe ſauing graces, true humilitie, godly ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, ioy in the Croſſe, patience, faith; being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3815:15"/> in bondage vnto the law and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But the ſanctified Chriſtian, who hath well learned Chriſt, whoſe heart faith hath thorowly purified: this man<note place="margin">Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 15. 9.</note> is not vnacquainted with the firſt be gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of ſauing repentance, as namely, godly ſorrow, indignation, with an holy reuenge vpon his vile affections. For, <hi>what ſeede is quickened except it die?</hi> yea <hi>we</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 36. Rom. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>are buried with Chriſt in baptiſme.</hi> See then the miſerable and vngrounded eſtate of the vnregenerate, though neuer ſo holie in his owne iudgement and other mens, yet being ignorant of Chriſtian buriall and death of ſinne, he is like a houſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ſandy foundation, ſubiect to the violent temptations of that prying and raging Serpent, ready to be toſſed with the waues of his owne corruptions, and drawne aſide by worldly enticements. From whence proceed ſo many euill ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings, ſmall care in bearing with, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the infirmities of the weake, yea<note place="margin">Chriſtians muſt examine well their mortification</note> that wofull ſinne of ſpirituall pride, but from vnmortified humours, and vnexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined conſciences? Many thinke, if they beleeue the Trinity with a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their ſins; all that God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3815:16"/> they haue performed; others, if they haue had ſome pangs of ſorrow; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if they be brought to leaue their groſſe ſinnes, they are not ſo bad as the worſt, therefore they imagine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be equall with the beſt.</p>
            <p>But the ſacred Scriptures teach the ground of true repentance to be farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, differing from this ſpeculatiue mortification, both in qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>titie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. To mortifie, in the Scriptures, is to crucifie, or apply that which will make dead? It is one thing to get ſinne aſleepe, but it is another thing to get it dead: for ſleepe may be procured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paine, but death cometh not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily without ſorrow and perplexitie. This mortifying therefore is a deſtroying of the whole body of ſinne, an extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the power and vigour of it. <hi>We</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 656.</note> 
               <hi>are grafied with Chriſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>into the ſimilitude of his death:</hi> which he in the next verſe expoundeth to be a <hi>crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the old man, and deſtroying of the whole body of ſinne.</hi> Now this crucifying or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying is expreſſed by diuers degrees: firſt, there is the wounding of ſin, when the ſinner is pricked with remorſe by the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3815:16"/> law: So were thoſe Conuerts at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon ſaid <hi>to be pricked in their hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37.</note> whereupon they cried, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaued?</hi> Secondly, a condemning of ſinne, when the ſinner examineth and iudgeth himſelf guilty before the Lord: and thus hath it bene with the Lords pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar from time to time, as may appeare in <hi>Dauid, Daniel, Iob,</hi> the Prodigall, and<note place="margin">Dan. 9. 7.</note> the Publican, who humbled themſelues as lyable to the iuſtice of the Almighty. Thirdly, the crucifying of ſin, when the ſinner racketh his owne ſoule by godly ſorrow, driuing in the nayles of Gods threatnings, reſtrayning his fleſh tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a ſpirituall reuenge: for ſome of the<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 11.</note> effects of godly ſorrow that cauſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance neuer to be repented of, are indignation and reuenge: Fourthly, the killing of ſinne, when the ſinner putteth off the body of ſin, and forſaketh his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill wayes. The Apoſtle forbiddeth ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and he addeth an vndeniable reaſon, <hi>Yee haue put off the old man with his workes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3. 9.</note> Yea he enioyneth not a partiall, but a thorowout mortification, ſhewing that he which is not inwardly and thorowly mortified, was neuer truely mortified.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3815:17"/> 
               <hi>Mortifie your members</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which are on the earth, fornication, vncleanneſſe, inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Where ſinne is truly mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, there is no liking of it in the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> 
               <hi>affection, euill concupiſcence, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, which is Idolatrie.</hi> Here the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would haue the conceptions and firſt inclinations to ſinne crucified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the originall of all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Hence we ſee, as alſo lamentable experience teſtifieth, that many build vpon ſeeming ſhews and vaine perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for that alteration that true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance maketh, cannot be found, and all for want of found mortification. For as there muſt be renouation in euery facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto all graces, ſo there muſt be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of all ſinnes in euery facultie: whereas it is otherwiſe in <hi>Agrippa</hi>-like Chriſtians and carnall Goſpellers, who vpon the quieting of conſcience, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a powerfull Miniſtery, dare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion themſelues according to the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and cuſtomes of the times in apparel and communication, not reſpecting the<note place="margin">The mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtian watcheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinnes of omiſſion. Phil. 2. 12.</note> vrgent neceſſitie of daily watchfulneſſe, with the conſtant practiſe of holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But the crucified Chriſtian, who ſeeketh and endeuoureth <hi>to worke out his ſaluation with feare and trembling,</hi> vpon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3815:17"/> his daily ſinnes executeth daily mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, concluding the neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed repentance from the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and his owne corruptions, and Whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne.</p>
            <p>Thus fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re haue we waded in the firſt vſe, proceed in order to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> In the ſecond place it taxeth thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities in the Sea of Rome, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualized and ballanced with the truth of ſacred Scriptures. But ſeeing that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon<note place="margin">Popery not able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures.</note> is fallen before the Arke, the fanne of the glorious Goſpell hauing already winn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wed the chaffe from the wheat: the miſts of darkneſſe being expelled by the Sunſhine of righteouſneſſe, and the power of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bell diſplayed by the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of him which rideth vpon the white horſe, infinite in wiſedome, and inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible in power and maieſtie: it is not my purpoſe therefore to be very large in this vſe of confutation: although my text would beare me out againſt all the proud brags of that Antichriſtian Synagogue. Well may we know that Papiſts, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the rabble of croking leſuites they are no babes, they can ſpeake for themſelues, or rather <hi>Baall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Though
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3815:18"/> their ſpeeches reſemble the ordinarie qualities and conditions of deceiptfull tradeſ-men, who when their wares for inſufficiency cannot ſell themſelues, their glozing tongues can get quicke and ſpeedy ſale for them: but for all their iugling, glozing, and diſſembling, they ſhall neuer cleare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from Chriſts ſentence againſt the Phariſes: <hi>In vaine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 15. 9.</note> 
               <hi>they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the precepts of men.</hi> This appeareth by<note place="margin">Papiſts build vpon man, but Chriſtians vpon God.</note> their ſandy vnſound foundations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they build, as namely, humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories, lying oracles, Decretals apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, preferring darkeneſſe before light, ſhadowes before ſubſtances, Traditions before commandements, yea the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before the creator. What can God do and the Pope cannot do? Nay, the Church is to iudge of the truth of the Scriptures. Tremble Babel, for the pride of the Church hath euer bene the ruine of the Church. But to inſiſt and ſearch more narrowlie, and to manifeſt more clearely the rotten ground-worke of this Romiſh building, the Rhemiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues comment vpon our text, and tell vs that the proper ſence is, That euery
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3815:18"/> thing that a man doth againſt his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſcience, is a ſinne, but they ſhew the ground neither for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor conſcience: ſomething muſt be vnderſtood which is not expreſſed, or elſe the conſequent muſt conclude, that a man can neither erre in iudgement nor conſcience: which well may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from ſome of their propoſitions, as namely this one; Ignorance the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of deuotion. For it is neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledge nor conſcience, when that faith will ſerue which is fixed vpon the Church, although that Church be grounded vpon the diuell himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, other ſtones there are which<note place="margin">Iuſtificatio eſt actus indiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus ac ſimul totus.</note> belong to this brittle foundation, as namely, that ſecond iuſtification by workes, as if there were a firſt and a laſt in the act of iuſtification; whereas it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a free acceptation of a mans perſon, yea a iuſtifying of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth: <hi>But to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>him that worketh not, but beleeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſſe.</hi> If any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man might haue merited any thing in the matter of iuſtification, it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3815:19"/> could not haue bene but <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> who were ſo abounding in the worke of the Lord, might haue gained ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for themſelues; but it is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as appeareth by their owne teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in facred Scripture. Lord, ſaith<note place="margin">Pſal 143. 2. 1. Cor. 4. 4. <hi>Iuſtificatio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primitur in Hebraico</hi> Hizdik Pro. 17. 15. &amp; in Graeco <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, for in thy ſight ſhall no fleſh liuing be iuſtified.</hi> The Apoſtle likewiſe ſaith, <hi>I haue in all good conſcience ſerued God vnto this day, neither know I any thing of my ſelfe: yet am I not thereby iuſtified.</hi> Beſides, the word, to iuſtifie, is oppoſed in the Scriptures to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſignifying an abſoluing or impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue iuſtice, <hi>It is God that iuſtifieth, who can condemne,</hi> Yea the bleſſed Apoſtle<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33. 34. Iſai. 50. 8. Act. 13. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aid to publiſh in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of the Iewes at Antioch, that <hi>From all things from which they could not be iuſtified by the Law of Moſes, by him,</hi> that is, by Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>euery one that beleeueth is iuſtified.</hi> Well ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. in feſt. Omnium Sanct. Serm.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vaehominum iuſtitiae quantumvis lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabili, ſi remota miſericordia Dei iudicetur,</hi> that is, Wo to the righteouſneſſe of man were it neuer ſo laudable, if God ſetting aſide mercy enter to iudge it. For this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3815:19"/> cauſe holy <hi>Iob</hi> is not aſhamed to confeſſe, that if he would diſpute with God, yet<note place="margin">Iob. 9. 3.</note> could he not make anſwer vnto one of a thouſand. Thus you ſee with what rubbiſh the foundation of the Romiſh Church is laid, of which a workman would be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yea neuer aduenture ſo great a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with ſo ſlippery a ground-worker but that the prophecy muſt be fulfilled in them as well as in other, namely Chriſt to be a ſtone to ſtumble at, and a rocke of offence, euen to them which ſtumble at<note place="margin">Eſay. 8. 14. 1. Pet. 2. 8.</note> the word, being diſobedient, vnto the which things they were euen ordained. Were it not ſo, how could they withſtand ſo plaine euidences of the ſpirit in ſacred Scriptures, as namely iuſtification only by faith without the works of the Law, figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; recorded by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles? Either it muſt be of grace, or of debt, but if debt, then were<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 8.</note> grace no more grace. In like manner they ſtand vpon <hi>Peters</hi> prerogatiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the other Apoſtles, which were a thing impoſſible to humaine reaſon, were they not giuen vp to diabolicall deluſions; for no other Apoſtle we reade of, that fell ſo often and grieuouſly as this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3815:20"/> man did. They tel vs that he walked vpon the water, ſo did none of the reſt. But what ſupernaturall act was this? for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the teſtimony of the Euangeliſt he bewraied diffidence and much weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and had not Chriſt caught him by the hand he had ſuncke. What vnity<note place="margin">Matth. 14. 30.</note> therefore or vniformity can there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Church of Chriſt and the Church of Antichriſt, when there is ſo<note place="margin">Rome cannot ſtand, for it wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth a ſound foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> great difference in the principles? Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore beſides all this, other ſtories there are, or rather vaniſhing rubbiſh, which prop and vphold this Romane Hierarchy, neither of Chriſts or any of his Apoſtles getting or laying; as namely that vngrounded doctrine of Tranſſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation lately hatched and decreed at the Councell of Lateran being 1215 yeares after Chriſt, vnder Pope <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the third: neuer taught by thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of great antiquity, namely, <hi>Irenaeus, Tertullian, Cyprian, Auguſtine.</hi> Yea the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts themſelues, <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> are ſufficient witneſſes of Chriſts owne words, who ſaid that he would drinke no more of the fruite of the vine,<note place="margin">Matth. 26. 29. Marke. 14. 25.</note> which was not bloud but wine, as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3815:20"/> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> both affirme. Theſe things being conſidered, who can iuſtly<note place="margin">Cal. lib. Inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. 13.</note> blame M. <hi>Caluin,</hi> thogh he ſay the mother &amp; organ of popiſh traditions was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an erronious zeale and prepoſterous humour deriued from Satan the father of lies and vngrounded Axiomes. And were not poore ignorant and deluded ſoules bewitched through the deceits of Satan and vanity of their minds, drawne aſide with thoſe ſpeculatiue ſhewes of Antichriſtian piety, and withall blinded<note place="margin">The doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church cannot be maintained by Scripture.</note> with thoſe falſe perſwaſions of admired Cardinals, how could it be but they ſhould relinquiſh ſuch impious falſities and counterfet holineſſe, grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon nothing but mans inuention? I could proceed in ſhewing the inſufficiency and weakneſſe of this declining Babell, the head corner ſtone which ſhould vphold the building being caſt aſide: but their apparent folly I ceaſſe to ſpeak of, it being ſufficiently manifeſted to the Church of God by the faithfull witneſſes of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. Let Ieſuits therefore, or rather<note place="margin">He that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth Chriſt truly cannot but preach good work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Iebuſites, maintaine their faithleſſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, as of free will, workes of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rogation, with ſuch like; yet let Sion fly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3815:21"/> to the Law and the Teſtimony; and if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is, as the Prophet ſaith, becauſe there is no light in them. And although they falſely<note place="margin">Eſay. 8. 20.</note> charge the Embaſſadors of Chriſt as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies vnto good workes, let them ſet them no higher then the Scriptures, and they ſhall ſet them no higher then we. <hi>For we are his workemanſhip, created in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 10</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes that we ſhould walke in them.</hi> Beſides, <hi>The wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our warfare are notcarnall, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, mighty through God to caſt downe</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>holds, caſting downe the imaginations and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery high thing that is exalted againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing euery thought into captiuity vnto the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> But where the Lord hath not a mouth to ſpeake, there his peculiar people may not haue an eare to heare; for Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not of faith is ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> In the third place it layeth open and bewrayeth the miſerable deluge of ſinne, in theſe laſt and worſt dayes. What aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? How do men wander from the Lord, denying by their works that God<note place="margin">The liues of men ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſhew what they are.</note> that made them, and Chriſt that bought them? How few are the families which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3815:21"/> ſquare their liues by the rule of faith? Are not the greateſt commandements the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneſt violated? Are not theſe dayes like the ſinfull dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> prophecied of by Chriſt, wherein this principal grace of faith is ſo meanly prized. But alas, ſins of all ſorts, in all ſorts of people, in <hi>fore &amp; Choro,</hi> both in Church and market. What iniquity can the corrupt heart of<note place="margin">Sinne did euer and ſhal euer abound on the earth.</note> man imagine, but it may be patronized by a practitioner, and warranted by a defender? How ridiculous and of baſe eſteeme is the life of faith? If any ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their liues, the diuell by wicked men will forthwith examine and cenſure<note place="margin">Satan can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion but not practiſe.</note> their heauenly courſes. To talke and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of religion Satan will ſometimes permit, but vniuerſall and conſtant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience he would neuer abide. If thou dare ſet thy face towards Sion, behold the northerne army of cruel Aſſirians. No affinitie with ſinne, ſmall frendſhip with the world. Faith and the world were euer at variance, <hi>For this is the victory which</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 1. 4</note> 
               <hi>ouer commeth the world, euen our faith. What concord can there be betwixt Chriſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall, light &amp; darkneſſe?</hi> Our Sauiour telleth the vnbeleeuing Iewes, <hi>That the world
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3815:22"/> cannot hate them, but him it hated:</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">Iohn. 7. 7.</note> followeth, not for iniury but for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, not for falſhood but for truth: he teſtified that the workes thereof were euill.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe that true pietie and grounded ſincerity is of ſo ſmal account, but becauſe the world of the vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn 5. 19.</note> lieth in wickednes, and faith to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections bringeth little content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? How can it be that oppreſſours, extortioners, vſurers, theſe idolatrou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worldlings, together with thouſands of delicious prodigals, ſhould entertaine the Goſpell: ſince <hi>Zacche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> muſt diuide his goods, <hi>Mathew</hi> muſt bid farewell to his place of cuſtomary receipt; yea the people of God muſt vſe this world as if<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 31. The life of faith very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> they vſed it not? How hard therefore will it be for ſuch as truſt in vncertaine ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to ſubiect themſelues to this life of faith? May not Gods Miniſters take vp a lamentation, What happy tidings from the word of faith which we preach? how is the way to euerlaſting bliſſe plainly beaten foorth, yet how few delight to walke in it? How ſluggiſh are our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon profeſſours, that cannot watch one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3815:22"/> houre? and how faithleſſe are thoſe back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding hypocrites, as if the vnchangeable poſſeſſour of heauen and earth were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, or vnable to recompence and fully reward his faithfull people?</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, that ſtreight is the way, and ſmall is the number that go it. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> is an vnruly heifer that will not be tamed. Euer haue Gods Saints bene like the ſhaking of an oliue after the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Wicked men are mad men, they will not be ordered; they are deafe men, they will not heare, charme the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer neuer ſo wiſely. If that be ſinne which is not done of ſaith, how wofull will it be with the greateſt number, who neither know nor beleeue, being blinde<note place="margin">Old naturall men are very miſerable, for they are full of ſinnes.</note> and diſſolute: hauing from their nonage to their old age wandred from the waies of God, being ſeuen fold more the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of hell then they were in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombes? If all actions that want faith be ſins, how many are the ſins of thoſe who were neuer enlightened with the knowledge of God? My text hath driuen me into ſuch a narrow ſtreight, &amp; ſo paled me in, that I cannot get liberty, either to licence the nouelties of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3815:23"/> or the blindneſſe of the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt, or the idolatry of the Papiſt, or the dreames of the Anabaptiſt, or the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie of the Phariſie. I am forced either<note place="margin">Gods word giueth no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to any ſin or ſinner.</note> to raze my text, or racke the conſcience of euery vnregenerate man; but ſeeing the groſſe ſinnes of our ſinfull times are ſo apparently arraigned and condemned in all generall teaching, and the light of conſcience, I deſire to deſcend into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>If therefore indifferent things muſt be of faith, at leaſt in the general, how much more matters of greater importance?<note place="margin">No life of faith without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>amination.</note> Where is the examination of thoughts, words, actions? Vnder what ſpirituall and heauenly promiſe do the workes of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitents conſiſt? What vſe can there be of faith, without the life of faith? For his will and promiſe are conſonants, they are companions, and cannot be diſioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The vncharitable railer that ſpends his time in whiſpering and back-biting the ſheepe of Chriſt, who deſire to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie<note place="margin">He which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Gods people wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth faith.</note> God in obedience, whereas loue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difieth and thinketh not euill; but where there is no loue (eſpecially to the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God) there is no faith: for faith, if it<note place="margin">Galat. 5. 6.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3815:23"/> be ſound, worketh by loue.</p>
            <p>In like manner the proud ſpirit and ſecure worldling, that eſteemeth the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull preaching of the Goſpel a meane and needleſſe labour, promiſing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe repentance without the conſtant and conſcionable vſe of the meanes, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at light the bleſſed doctrine of voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, although in an audible voyce it was hard from heauen, <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed heare him.</hi> And the Apoſtle dare confidently affirme<note place="margin">Matth. 17. 5. Rom. 10. 17. 41.</note> both by doctrine and experience. That faith commeth by hearing, and no ſound hearing without a preacher: yea he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the Goſpell of Chriſt to be<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> the power of God, to ſaluation to euery beleeuer. And what good was done in Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inth or Galatia, he affirmeth that through Chriſt by his meanes it was wrought; <hi>In Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ſaith he to the Church at Corinth, <hi>I haue begotten you</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>through the Gospell:</hi> and expoſtulateth the matter with the Church at Galatia:<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Thus receiued ye the Spirit by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the workes of the Law, or by the hearing of faith preached?</hi> Thus then we ſee theſe wofull contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of able and conſcionable Miniſters,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3815:24"/> ground vpon no better a foundation then their corrupted imagination. They<note place="margin">It is a note of a wicked man not to loue and frequent the meanes of grace.</note> will not be guided by God nor eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Chriſt, but chuſe rather to wander in the wilderneſſe of naked hope, openly deſcrying and publiſhing that condemnation which is in the world, ſpoken of by our Sauiour, Iohn 3. 19. 20. <hi>This is the condemnation, that light</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>is come into the world, and men loued dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rather then light, becauſe their deedes were e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill: for euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an that euill doth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the light, neither commeth to light, leſt his deedes ſhould be reprooued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others, through the blindneſſe of their vnderſtanding and peruerſneſſe of their wills and affections, account the<note place="margin">He that knoweth not Gods day and worſhip, knoweth not God.</note> Lords day, but as the Scholler doth the Thurſday<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely a day of ſport and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, examining more their app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rell the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the day or their hearts; as alſo their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and baſe companions more then the aſſembly of Saints in the Sanctuary. Whence it commeth to paſſe that they neither prepare to, nor take any delight in Gods publike worſhip. The reaſon is, becauſe they ground not on faith, being both ignorant of the myſtery of the day
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3815:24"/> wherein our chiefeſt happineſſe is reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; as alſo being led by their owne ſenſualities and carnall appetites, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing rather the direction of their own wils then the guide of faith. Thus as they are grounded vpon themſelues, ſo they remaine ignorant of Chriſt and ſecrets of the Goſpell, and for want of a ſenſible<note place="margin">He that thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth not for knowledge hath no care to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e well.</note> thirſt and appetite vnto the word, ſhall neuer be able to liue the life of faith, or walke the way to euerlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But let vs come to more cloſe and vnwarrantable courſes of men, not grounded on this rocke of faith.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt, when we receiue the bleſſings of God not ſanctified by the word and prayer, whereas the Apoſtle teacheth<note place="margin">1. Timoth. 4. 4.</note> that euery creature of God is good, and nothing ought to be refuſed if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued<note place="margin">God is to be remembred in all his bleſſings.</note> with thankeſ-giuing. Wherein is implyed the contrary, that the creatures are not good vnto me without thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing: the reaſon followeth, for they are ſanctified by the word of God and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and not ſanctified without it. Beſides the examples in former times, the poore maides of <hi>Ramath Zophim</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> that<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9. 13.</note> the people would eate no meate vntill
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3815:25"/> the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> had bleſſed the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9. 13. Iohn 6. 11.</note> Yea Chriſt himſelfe did neuer eate meat but he practiſed this duty; and the Apoſtle would eate no bread, but firſt gaue thanks in the preſence of them<note place="margin">Acts 27. 35.</note> all: and commandeth it as a ſpeciall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>In all things giue thankes:</hi> and addeth<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5. 18.</note> this reaſon, <hi>for this is the will of God.</hi> If theſe Scriptures and examples were well weighed, there would not be ſuch bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh receiuing of the creatures as there<note place="margin">He that ſeeth God in the leſſer bleſſing wil praiſe him for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> commonly is. Nay, many that do coldly performe this duty, if God euer enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them to ſee further the neceſſitie and excellencie of this duty, they will not neglect to bleſſe the Lord for greater mercies; they will (I ſay) be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to performe and offer vp morning and euening Sacrifices.</p>
            <p>It would be holden a very inhuman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſhamefull dealing, to forget the kindneſſes of men; how vnnaturall then is it, and intollerable, to forget ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Learne to bleſſe God by the light of nature.</note> renewed mercies of the Lord? He therefore that is without ſobriety, praier and thankeſgiuing in the vſe of Gods creatures, plainly manifeſteth, that he neither by faith dependeth on God, nor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3815:25"/> in faith receiueth his bleſſings; but <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, when men confeſſe their ſinnes in generall, and cry for pardon for them; but they cannot credit theſe two things: Firſt, that all thoughts, words;<note place="margin">Pure actions are ſtrained actions.</note> and actions muſt be ſtrained through faith, or elſe they will be impure. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that God forgiueth no more knowne ſinnes then a man earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth to forſake, they being blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">Sin is forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God when it is mortified in vs.</note> out of Gods regiſter when they are dead in vs: the power and vigor of them being extinguiſhed, and we in all things as ready to glorifie God, as we would haue him to glorifie vs. But alas, when prayers are not grounded vpon a liuely ſenſe of ſinne, and Gods eternall ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance due vnto them; as alſo godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and faith in the promiſes: how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly do men turne to their old vomite, and filthy wallowing in the vncleannes of ſinne? cauſing ſound iudgement and grounded reaſon to ſubſcribe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe<note place="margin">Where there is not theſenſe of ſin, there cannot be the forſaking of ſinne.</note> will and carnall affection, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Iſhmael</hi> before <hi>Iſaac, Eſau</hi> before <hi>Iacob, Zidkijah</hi> before <hi>Michaiah,</hi> the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes before Chriſt, cuſtome before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3815:26"/> tradition before the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus for want of diuine illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as alſo a correſpondencie betwixt their ſupplication and conuerſation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and affection, their vngrounded prayers become a vaine lip-labour, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, and abhominable in the eares of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when men apparell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues beyond their eſtate, and aboue their degrees, although God hath threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to viſite all ſuch as weare ſtrange at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 9.</note> and hath granted grounds for our attire, namely the preſidence of the wiſe, graue, and godly of that degree we liue in. <hi>Whatſoeuer things are pure, honeſt, and of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 8.</note> 
               <hi>good report</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vertue, or any praiſe, thinke on theſe things which you haue both heard and ſeene in me.</hi> But the wantons of our dayes turne their eyes from Gods booke and people, fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vpon their owne fancies and backs of <hi>Ieſabels,</hi> imagining that if they be out of the faſhion, they be out of the world. Hence it followeth, that ſeruants attire themſelues like their Maſters, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters like Courtiers, Yeomen like Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Schollers like Souldiers. Thus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3815:26"/> vnſeemely and vnwarrantably do men and women apparell themſelues, preferring the garments of corruption before the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt: oftentimes againſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, equitie, and common honeſtie, cutting their ſuites in another mans cloth, being daily vagrants from the life of God and ground of faith. But <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, when men liue vpon the ſweate of other mens browes, cruſhing the back of the diligent workman. Such are wandring vagabonds, prying buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies,<note place="margin">Theſe and ſuch like, ſin againſt the ſecond Table</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lliſh tale-bearers, gameſters, ſtage-players, who ſinfully tranſgreſſe the law of charity, walking in the wayes of <hi>Balaam</hi> who loued the wages of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, being without God and without Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, when with offence, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out edification we vſe things of an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature, whereas the Apoſtle tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that in ſome caſes, and amongſt ſome perſons, <hi>it is euill to eate with offence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> meaning to the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, not wilfull. For the law of loue and ſpirit bindeth where<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the law of commandements bindeth not: <hi>All things are lawfull for me, but all</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3815:27"/> 
               <hi>things are not expedient; all things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me,</hi> but <hi>all things edifie not.</hi> Now whatſoeuer is not expedient nor profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, may not accidentally be lawfull,<note place="margin">In ſome caſes things lawfull become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</note> although in it ſelfe it may be ſo. It is true, that there is no indifferent thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane of it ſelfe, but <hi>Vnto him</hi> (ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle) <hi>that iudgeth any thing to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 14.</note> 
               <hi>be vncleane, to him it is vncleane.</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite therefore, that we ſtand faſt in the libertie wherein Chriſt hath ſet vs free:<note place="margin">Galat. 5. 1.</note> yet withall, we muſt beware that we giue offence neither to Iew nor Gentile,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 32.</note> nor to the Church of God. And for the better doing of this, we muſt looke to<note place="margin">The edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of the Church muſt be a thing deare vnto vs.</note> the right vſing of things indifferent: for we eaſily infringe and abuſe our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an libertie. There be three principall grounds or maine directions for the well vſing and ordering of things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when we vſe them lawfully, that is, to Gods glorie, not ſuperſtition or prophaneneſſe. Therefore the Apoſtle commandeth, that <hi>Whether we eate or</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 31.</note> 
               <hi>drinke, or whatſoeuer we do, we do all to the glorie of God.</hi> Thus in eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which are in themſelues things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3815:27"/> we are to ſeeke God. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when we vſe them profitably, to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, the good of man, <hi>All things</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>muſt profit;</hi> yea <hi>Euery</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 2.</note> 
               <hi>man muſt pleaſe his neighbour, in that which is good, as Chriſt pleaſed not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but others.</hi> This belongeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the weake and ignorant that<note place="margin">Gods glorie and mans good, the maine ends of all our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</note> may be in the Church, whom I am bound to edifie, ſupport, build vp, and not by any meanes to weaken or grieue, much leſſe deſtroy, although the thing be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo lawfull in it ſelfe. Thirdly, when we vſe them proportionably, that is, in ſobrietie, not failing in the manner, nor exceeding in the meaſure, but ſo vſing them as they further vs in all duties of godlineſſe, being alwayes vigilant ouer our affections, leſt we be brought into bondage by them. Let vs rather be ſaid to enioy them, then they vs. Thus for the ſtrong Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>But the weake conſcience may here<note place="margin">Duties to be done, and not ſimply groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the word, muſt neceſſarily be examined.</note> obiect: How ſhall I do all things of faith, ſeeing there are ſo many lawes which are not ſimply preſcribed in the Word? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Lawes that ſimply and primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binde in conſcience, are ſuch as binde
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3815:28"/> though there were no humane lawes to vrge them; ſuch as preaching, hearing, praying, with others of the ſame qualitie and neceſſitie. Thus the Apoſtle is ſaid to preach <hi>Chriſt crucified,</hi> although vnto<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the Iewes a ſtumbling blocke, and to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>fooliſhneſſe.</hi> And <hi>Daniel</hi> is ſaid to pray three times a day, and praiſe his God dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, albeit the King and the people rage at him. For this cauſe may it be lawfull to compell the Papiſt to come to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ordinances and publike worſhip of God, albeit it ſeeme to offend them: for good king <hi>Ioſias made a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enant with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 34. 32</note> 
               <hi>Lord and cauſed all his people to ſtand to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other lawes there are which do not ſimply &amp; primarily binde in conſcience, but ſecondarily and in reſpect: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although the wholeſome lawes of the Magiſtrate bind not ſimply &amp; prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the conſcience, but ſecondarily, yet<note place="margin">Magiſtrates muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in all lawful things.</note> we muſt obey their wholſome lawes for conſcience ſake, our conſciences being bound, not by the law of the Magiſtrate, but by Gods law, which bindeth to the obedience of the Magiſtrates lawes in all lawfull and honeſt things: according to the rule of the Apoſtle, Romans 13. 5.<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3815:28"/> 
               <hi>Ye muſt be ſubiect for conſcience ſake.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are we curbed any whit in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, ſince vnto humane lawes which fight not with Gods lawes, the outward man is bound directly, and not the inward but by accident.</p>
            <p>The law therefore that forbiddeth the<note place="margin">All humane lawes muſt tend towards God and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note> frequenting of Alehouſes, for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of drunkenneſſe, is by good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent grounded vpon the Scripture: alſo the law that forbiddeth the wearing of weapons, for the auoyding of bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and ſuch like. So likewiſe Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall lawes, helping forward towards the obſeruation of the firſt and ſecond Table, although they binde not in particular, yet in the generall; as the place of Gods worſhip, the time, maintenance for the Miniſters, ſilence in the Church, with ſuch like.</p>
            <p>The Arrian heretiks refuſed the word<note place="margin">Some things are lawfull &amp; agreeable to the Scriptures which are not ſimply ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and denyed Chriſt to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, of the ſame ſubſtance with the Father, becauſe it was a word no where found in the Scriptures. But <hi>Athanaſius</hi> anſwereth, that <hi>Etſi haec vox in Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris non rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritur, habere tamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam quam Scripturae volunt:</hi> that is, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3815:29"/> the word it ſelfe be not found in the Scriptures, yet it hath that ſence which the Scriptures do allow of.</p>
            <p>There are alſo other ciuill and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall orders, which do binde neither generally nor ſimply, but accidentally, in reſpect of the contempt of authoritie, and ſcandall that may enſue vpon the breaking of order. Now the weake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is in things indifferent moſt like to ſtumble, they wanting expreſſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Word, and he feareth to enterpriſe any action without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. In which caſes, tender conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">Tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences muſt not be racked</note> muſt be tendered rather then racked by authoritie. For, be the things neuer ſo lawfull in themſelues, be they neuer ſo generally entertained in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practiſe of others, yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vtterly vnlawfull to me, without ſuch information: for the Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is, <hi>Let euery man be fully perſwaded</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 5.</note> 
               <hi>in his minde.</hi> It ſtandeth therefore euerie Chriſtian vpon, to examine narrowly all his actions, eſpecially his diuine and ſpirituall duties, yea ſurely to be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all matters concerning the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3815:29"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Whether hath the Prince power to make Eccleſiaſticall lawes and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his owne, ſince there is one Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer<note place="margin">Iam. 4. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which is able to ſaue and to deſtroy? Yea, either edicts authoriſing and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the lawes of the Law-giuer, or conſtitutions circumſtantiall and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which may vary according to the variableneſſe of times, places, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Churches.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles rule being euer obſerued,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions muſt tend to order decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and remaineth as variable.</note> namely, that they tend to order, decency &amp; edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beſides, that al ſuch change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſtitutions be not vrged as any part of Gods eſſentiall worſhip, or as neceſſary to ſaluation, or equalized with the law of God; neither may they by their multitude obſcure the glory of Chriſt in his ordinances: but ſuch lawes as are made vniuſtly, or command vnlawfull things, do binde neither in generall nor particular, neither in themſelues nor accidentally, and therefore cannot be of faith. Now the Church of Rome maketh<note place="margin">Great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Church of Rome and the Church of England.</note> lawes and ordaineth conſtitutions, not onely <hi>Extrafidem</hi> without faith, but alſo <hi>contrafidem,</hi> againſt faith, and to bind the conſcience in paine of mortall ſinne,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3815:30"/> laying grieuous burthens vpon mens ſhoulders, heauie to be borne.</p>
            <p>And thus farre in the third vſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed we in order to the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> In the fourth place it teacheth Gods Miniſters to preach the Scriptures as in<note place="margin">Gods mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters muſt preach Gods word. 2. Tim. 4. 1. 2.</note> reſpect of the neceſſity thereof, all our actions being to be done of faith; ſo alſo from the direction of the Apoſtle, who ſaith to <hi>Timothy, Preach the word.</hi> Nay we haue the example of Chriſt, who prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets himſelfe. The Scribe demanding the way to life, Chriſt anſwereth by interrogation, What<note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> is written in the law, how readeſt thou? Againe, he entring into a Synagogue at Nazareth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sabboth (it being his<note place="margin">Luke. 4. 17.</note> ordinary cuſtome by the teſtimony of the Euangeliſt) and a booke of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſaiah</hi> being deliuered him, he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth the booke, and findeth it written thus, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is vpon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath anointed me, that I ſhold preach the Gospell to the poore, &amp;c.</hi> The which he expoundeth and applyeth, as plainly appeareth in the verſes following: yea he vrgeth it as a duty vpon the people for to heare <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets: <hi>They
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3815:30"/> haue Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Luke 16. 29.</note> 
               <hi>let them heare them</hi> Now what made way for Antichriſt, but leauing of the Scriptures? From whence ariſeth ſchiſme, hereſie, together with groſſe idolatry,<note place="margin">The caſting aſide of the word is the high way to ſchiſme, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. and groſſe Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> but from ignorance in the Scriptures? For opinion and ſenſe may faile and erre, when faith rightly grounded vpon the word cannot. What hath cauſed ſo many ſects to ſpring vp in the boſome of the Church, as Donatiſts, Familiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Anabaptiſts, but want of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Scripture with Scripture? When men want indifferent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares and hearts, their affections rather inclining to cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſecurity and liberty, and their iudgements blinded through pride and ſelfe-loue, how ſoone, I ſay, are ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, drawne away and corrupted? Therefore as it is a duty to ſearch the Scriptures, they being the ground of faith, and pillar of truth: ſo it behoueth the Lords embaſſadors to come to the people, with, not Thus ſay I, but Thus ſaith the Lord. For what wiſe man will<note place="margin">The word of God vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters office and authority</note> credit euery heare-ſay? or what ſubiect wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l yeeld reſpect to ſuch an one as cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiteth the kings Embaſſador, hauing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3815:31"/> neither his Maieſties Armes nor Seale. I will not deny, but it is a bleſſed thing to teach Gods truth from a ſanctified ſpirit: for who is able to direct in that myſticall doctrine of regeneration ſo well as he that is regenerate himſelfe? or what art is able to deſcribe and teach like experience? It was an infallible truth, and grounded certenty, ſufficiently perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wiſe men, that in Bethleem<note place="margin">Mich. 5. 2. Matth 2. 9.</note> was borne Chriſt the king of the Iewes, when the prophecy of the Prophets, and the conducting ſtarre paralleled both, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting vnto one and the ſame place. As ſure and credible will it be, when Gods ſacred Spirit in vs ſhall ſympathiſe with<note place="margin">Gods word and his Spirit make a ſweet harmony in his Miniſters.</note> his reuealed truth. But if ſenſe prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly faile without the guide of faith, then beware of ſhip wracke, for <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not of faith is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then, as in a glaſſe, the duty of all Gods embaſſadors; for as we may not preach our ſelues, but Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, ſo may we not deliuer a parcell of the Scriptures, or diuulge them partially. The true treaſure and diuine Oracles of the Almighty require faithfulneſſe: for ſo ought ſtewards to be found faithfull.<note place="margin">Cor. 4. 2.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3815:31"/> Gods truth as it is, ſo it muſt be taught. The word of truth deſerueth true diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">The whole word of God muſt be taught.</note> as alſo right application, whereby the whole counſel of God may be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Saints. For oftentimes the want of comparing Scripture with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and diſtinguiſhing of times, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth an Ataxie or confuſion in the Churches of God. To inſtance in ſome particulars and lamentable preſidents: The cauils and innouations of that Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall Sect, who ſay that the New Teſtament is ſufficient to ſaluation, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Old vnneceſſary and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and they ground themſelues vpon theſe Scriptures, 2. Cor. 3. 6. and 14. <hi>Who</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 6. 14 16.</note> 
               <hi>hath made vs able Miniſters of the New Teſtament; not of the letter, but of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: for the letter killeth, but the Spirit gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life. Moſes</hi> (ſay they) <hi>had a couering,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anabaptiſts very proud and groſly ignorant.</note> 
               <hi>which in Chriſt is taken away.</hi> But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith not, that <hi>Moſes</hi> is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but the veile is taken away. For the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the illumination and conuerſion of the Iewes to Chriſt, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the ſixteenth verſe: <hi>Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, when their hearts ſhall be turned to the Lord, the veile ſhall be taken away.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3815:32"/> the ſhadows and ceremonies muſt needes be taken away, when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is come: but Chriſt was not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed or typified in the moral law, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that cannot vtterly be taken away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 17. 18.</note> for his comming was not to aboliſh it, but to fulfill it: therefore the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is both neceſſary and profitable. Furthermore, what although the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teach, that <hi>the letter killeth,</hi> but <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines good vſe of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law, both for repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and life.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit giueth life,</hi> doth he thereby any thing elſe but ſhew the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Law and the Goſpel? namely, that the one is able to do nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the orga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit cannot be properly ſaid to be the Law but the Goſpell, ſince the Law hath no power to regenerate, but the Goſpell; yet in regeneration and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, the Law hath it worke and vſe, and therefore cannot be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Another ground they haue in <hi>Matth.</hi> 17. 5. Chriſt (ſay they) by the command<note place="margin">Matth. 17. 5.</note> of the Father, is onely to be heard: but, to heare <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets of Chriſt, is to heare Chriſt. Beſides, it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Sonne himſelfe, who was equall with the Father, <hi>They haue Moſes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16. 39.</note>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3815:32"/> 
               <hi>and the Prophets, let them heare them.</hi> Yea he telleth the Iewes, that <hi>If they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 47.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes, they would haue beleeued him, for he wrote of him.</hi> Againe, was there any oppoſition in the Spirit of Chriſt, which was both in <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 10. 11 The doctrine of Moſes and the Prophets rightly appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</note> and Chriſt? <hi>Of this ſaluation</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the Prophets haue enquired and ſearched, which propheſied of the grace that ſhould come vnto you. Searching when or what time, the Spirit which teſtified before of Chriſt, which was in them, ſhould declare the ſufferings that ſhould come vnto Chriſt, and the glorie that ſhould follow.</hi> Yea the ſame Apoſtle affirmeth, that <hi>We haue a</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 19.</note> 
               <hi>moſt ſure word of the Prophets.</hi> What let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth then, but we may attend vnto the ſound doctrine of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? Furthermore, the teſtimonie of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is pregnant to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, who auoucheth, <hi>That the whole</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 16. Corruption needeth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection as well as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Reproofes ſometimes very needfull.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture is giuen by inspiration of God, and is profitable to teach, improue, correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe:</hi> therefore the whole Scripture is neceſſarie, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtanding in neede of it, either for ground of faith, or rule of obedience, both in his generall &amp; particular calling.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3815:33"/>
            <p>Like vnto theſe dreames, is the errour of many Libertines, who ground vpon that ſaying in <hi>Ieremiah, After thoſe dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 31. 33.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord, I will put my Lawes in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inward parts, and write them in their hearts:</hi> as alſo vpon that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Yee are our Epiſtle, written, not with inke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>but with the Spirit of the liuing God.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be true, that the knowledge of the Law may be written naturally in mens hearts, yet he commanded the ſame to be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in two tables of ſtone. For, how doth the Lord write this Law in our hearts? How doth he ſeale vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the couenant of our reconciliation and regeneration by the finger of his<note place="margin">The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit pipe to conuey grace into our harts</note> Spirit, but by the doctrine of the Law and Goſpell, preached, heard, written, read, meditated? Or how could the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles call themſelues the Preachers of the New Teſtament, if the Goſpel could not be preached? And in vaine ſhould Chriſt bid vs, <hi>Search the Scriptures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 39.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, the Euangeliſts and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles call their doctrine, which was the New Teſtament, a Scripture or Writing, as appeareth by that teſtimony of <hi>Luke,</hi> who thought it meete to write <hi>Thoſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 3.</note>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3815:33"/> 
               <hi>things which he had diligently ſearched out:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 3.</note> as alſo, <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth, who ſaith, <hi>That theſe things are written that ye may beleeue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 20. 31.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> thought it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to write, as is plaine in his Epiſtles.<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 1.</note> Thus we ſee that the men of God, and<note place="margin">The Spirit of God in the hearts of his people, and his word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Miniſters of the Goſpell, wrote by the Spirit the Goſpell with inke: the hearts of true beleeuers ſanctified by the Spirit through the preaching of the Goſpel, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering correſpondently that word which was both written and preached; as was euident among thoſe Conuerts at Corinth, <hi>in whom was manifeſt</hi> the power of the Goſpell: the preaching of faith being the power of God to ſaluation, to<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> euery one that doth beleeue.</p>
            <p>We ſee then by wofull experience, that Satan tranſforming himſelfe into an<note place="margin">It is the work of Satan to draw men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods word, which is the ground of faith.</note> Angell of light, ſeeketh to ground many a poore ſoule vpon ſeeming ſhadowes, drawing them from the rocke of refuge, and certenty, namely, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Euangeliſts and Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt, who haue written and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as the Spirit directed and gaue them vtterance. Were not therefore the proud Anabaptiſt fuller of conceit then iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3815:34"/> he would neuer paraphraſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures in that manner as he doth; as I haue already ſhewed, and will further ſhew in one inſtance. Chriſt ſaith, Mathew 5. 34. <hi>Sweare not at all:</hi> therefore,<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 34.</note> ſaith he, it is not lawfull in any caſe to ſweare. Whereas the Lord (vpon neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) hath commended and commanded a lawfull oath, warranting the ſame both by example and precept, as appeareth in Deut. 6. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 13.</note> 
               <hi>God, and ſerue him, and ſhalt ſweare by his Name.</hi> Yea, the Apoſtle teſtifieth, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon neceſſity an oath to be a very good thing: <hi>An oath</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for confirmation</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 6. 16.</note> 
               <hi>is the end of all ſtrife.</hi> Thus by conceited expoſition would this ſect of people bring Chriſt to abrogate his Fathers law, and derogate from his Fathers glorie;<note place="margin">A proud ſpirit vnfit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Scripture.</note> whereas our Sauiour meaneth nothing leſſe: for his purpoſe is nothing elſe but to expound the Law, and deliuer it from the groſſe corruptions and deprauations<note place="margin">He that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, neither reſpecteth God nor Chriſt.</note> of the Scribes and Phariſes. For they taught, that the third commandement was to be vnderſtood of periurie onely, or falſe ſwearing: therefore our Sauiour ſheweth, that in this commandement is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3815:34"/> forbidden, not onely periury and falſe ſwearing by the Name of God, but alſo all raſh and ordinary ſwearing in our common talke, whether by the Name of God, or any of his creatures; becauſe ſwearing amiſſe by them redoundeth to his diſhonour. He therefore here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth all needeleſſe and ſuperfluous<note place="margin">All needleſſe ſwearing is much forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Scripture.</note> oathes in our ordinary communication. And as theſe do erre, not knowing nor vnderſtanding the Scriptures, ſo do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, as namely, the <hi>Carnall cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> that ioyneth himſelfe with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblies, partaking of the ſame word and Sacraments with the Saints of God: But this man would haue one line to be ſufficient vnto ſaluation; for he findeth it written in the Scriptures, <hi>That</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 36. Naturall men would haue all, but they would do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</note> 
               <hi>he which beleeueth in the Sonne hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> But if this man reade forward, he ſhall ſee and finde, <hi>That he which obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Sonne ſhall not ſee life.</hi> Such will like the doctrine of faith, but they cannot well brooke the doctrine of repentance. But, if they attend, or liſt to heare, they ſhall heare Chriſt to be as rigorous as his Father, both in ſummoning all men<note place="margin">Marke 1. 15. Luke 13. 5.</note> to repent, as alſo in threatning woes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3815:35"/> impenitents. The Apoſtles, as they preach faith, ſo they preach ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication<note place="margin">Acts 2. 38.</note> and amendment of life: for it is the abſolute will of God, that <hi>we ſhould</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſal 43 1. Pet. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>be holy as the Lord our God is holy.</hi> The whole word of the Lord therefore muſt be deliuered by the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, that the whole courſes of mens liues may be guided by the rule of faith. Chriſt and his Apoſtles did not alwayes<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 10. 11</note> preach faith, but according to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of people and Churches, ſo was their doctrine, diuiding the word of truth aright. Amongſt them of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, the Apoſtle preſſeth the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith, but where the Goſpell was eſtabliſhed, he vnfoldeth further<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 34. Tit. 2. 1. 2. 1. Tim. 6. 17. 18.</note> the myſterie of godlineſſe, teaching o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces and gracious duties neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and appertaining to Chriſtian life.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee the wiſedome of God, in ſcattering the Scriptures, not onely for the making his people more diligent in ſearching them, but alſo, that they may<note place="margin">The Browniſt a wreſter of holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in many things.</note> remaine in his iuſt iudgement a ſtone to ſtumble at, euen to ſuch as are diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and vnbeleeuing. Furthermore, would the Familiſt and Separatiſt take
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3815:35"/> any paines in comparing Scripture with Scripture, they ſhould finde but weake grounds for their indiſcreet and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceedings. For although they are bold and peremptory in alledging Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet if they were able to ſee their pride and ignorance, they ſhould finde but a ſlippery ground-worke to vphold and maintaine their wilfull ſeparation. The alledging of Scripture literally and ſolely without compariſon, will no more helpe, in ſome caſes, then bare ſufferings without the cauſe, will helpe a man to be<note place="margin">The diuell cunning in quoting Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Pſal. 91. 11. Matth. 4. 6.</note> a Chriſtian. The diuell, for his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, hath alledged Scripture; he can tell Chriſt it is written, <hi>That the Lord had giuen his Angels charge ouer him, and with their hands they ſhould lift him vp, that at any time he daſh not his foote againſt a ſtone;</hi> therefore what if he caſt himſelfe downe from the pinacle of the Temple? But the Lord Ieſus knew, that although this Scripture was truth, yet it was no warrant for him to ſubiect himſelfe to<note place="margin">Chriſtians muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to euerie quoter of Scripture.</note> Satans wil, or enterpriſe ſuch a needleſſe action. And can we perſwade our ſelues that he laboureth not to traine vp as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he can in ſuch cunning ſophiſtry?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3815:36"/> will he leaue any arrow in his quiuer vnſhot before he will be conquered? When humane learning cannot ſerue, he<note place="margin">Satan a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſophiſter</note> will not be afraid to vrge diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Wofull experience witneſſeth his working vpon the corruptions of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt profeſſours, cauſing their pride, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and hypocriſie to end in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſme, Browniſme, and Apoſtacie. But let vs ſearch ſome of their maineſt grounds. The firſt place which I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe<note place="margin">The ground of Separatiſts.</note> to ſhew, is in the 1. Corinthians 5. 6. 7. 11. <hi>A little leauen doth leauen the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. 6. 7. 11</note> 
               <hi>whole lumpe; purge out therefore the old leauen. If any which is called a brother be a fornicatour, or an idolater, or couetous, or a rayler, or drunkard, or extortioner, with ſuch an one eate not.</hi> But the Apoſtle ſaith not,<note place="margin">Particulars will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hold to maintaine generals.</note> Eate not with any that is diſobedient, but with a brother. There were many that denyed the reſurrection; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not theſe to be caſt forth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he ſay, that when he ſhall come to them, he will caſt all ſuch foorth as haue not repented of their fornication<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 21.</note> and wantonneſſe, but bewaile them. The perſon therefore that may not be eaten with, is a brother, a Chriſtian by name,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3815:36"/> one excommunicated: the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<note place="margin">Our ſharpe dealing with others muſt be ſugred with loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. 2. Theſſ. 3. 14. 15.</note> was not to root him out, but to plant him in. For this muſt be done, that he might be aſhamed; neither was he to be accounted as an enemy, but admoniſhed as a brother.</p>
            <p>The holy Fathers, preſently after the primitiue times, were troubled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues<note place="margin">The Church euer troubled with ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes.</note> with ſuch ſchiſmaticall Donatiſts, as namely, <hi>Parmenian,</hi> and <hi>Creſconius</hi> with others, who grounded themſelues vpon this Scripture, with ſuch like. Vnto whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth in this manner.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fratrum. i. Chriſtianorum intus in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſocietate conſtitutorum in aliquo tali peccalo fueri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſus vt Anathemate dign us habea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, fiat hoc vbi periculum ſchiſmatis nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt, &amp;c. Auguſt. cont. Auguſt. cont. Parm. lib. 3. cap.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When any of the brethren, that is, of the Chriſtians which haue place within in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church, be taken in ſome ſuch ſin, that he may be counted worthy to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, let it be done where there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a ſchiſme, This man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite non ad eradicandum ſed ad corrigendum. Caſt out, that he being ſtricken through feare, may be healed through ſhame: When ſeeing himſelfe excommunicated of the whole Church, he cannot finde a multitude to be of his fellowſhip, with whom he may reioyce in his fin, and inſult ouer the good.</hi> We ſee here by the teſtimony of the Father, as alſo by the praſtiſe of the Apoſtle, that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3815:37"/> may not be reiected, much leſſe whole Churches, as theſe Separatiſts dreame, <hi>Leſt while we go about to plucke vp</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the tares, we plucke vp the wheat likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Scriptures they ground vpon, as theſe out of the Prophets <hi>Ieremiah. 23. 28. What hath the chaffe to do with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 25. 28.</note> 
               <hi>wheate?</hi> Alſo vpon that in <hi>Eſaiah 52. 11. Depart, depart, come out from thence, touch</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 52. 11.</note> 
               <hi>no vncleane things, come out from the middeſt thereof, and ſeparate your ſelues you that beare the veſſels of the Lord.</hi> But when was this ſeparation? was it not when Babel was incurable &amp; neare vnto deſtruction? Otherwiſe the Prophets themſelues, yea Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſinned when they were in the Temple with vngodly multitudes. Hath not the chaffe bene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<note place="margin">The Church was neuer without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</note> with the wheate? Is there no chaffe at Amſterdam? or hath God no people but there? Hath there not bene hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites in the Church? and who are worſe, or how ſhall they be winnowed before the ſeparating Angell come with his<note place="margin">The chaffe and the wheat muſt be together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntill the laſt day.</note> winnowing fan? The cauſe now of their ſeparation is becauſe we are Babiloniſh; the Church of England (ſay they) is ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous and antichriſtian. Admit we were
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3815:37"/> ſo, which is a ſhameleſſe ſlander, yet this is no ground for preſent and ſudden cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſeparation.<note place="margin">If theſe who were extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily gifted hauing withal the ſpirit of diſcerning, ſeparated not, what ground hath the Brouniſt?</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Iewes and falſe teachers were ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious enough, yet <hi>Paul</hi> remained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, vntill the Lord called him from thence to go preach vnto them of the vncircumciſion. And ſo did Chriſt. For what doth the Lord require more then a diſioyning in affection &amp; fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? Beſides, if all humane conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be ſimply ſinnes, then were all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue &amp; reformed Churches idolatrous and vncleane, and the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues guilty of ſinne for communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with ſuch. Nay further, who may communicate with the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, although he digreſſe from the ſame order himſelfe? <hi>For we may not ſit at</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 10. chap. 10. 21.</note> 
               <hi>the Idols table.</hi> Therefore vntill they proue vs Babiloniſh, and beſides all that, to be incurable, their pretended grounds ſhall end in meeare conceits, for <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of faith is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt ſort or ſect that I purpoſe to meddle with, who would faine ſeeke a ſtaffe from Scripture to hold themſelues by, is the Papiſt. One of their maineſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3815:38"/> grounds is in the Epſtile of <hi>Iames 2. 24. Ye ſee then, how that of workes a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 24.</note> 
               <hi>and not of faith onely.</hi> Here they ground their ſecond iuſtification; for<note place="margin">Second iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication a mere inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> they would haue him that is iuſt, to be more iuſtified, although compariſons of greater and leſſer do not make a ſeuerall kind, but declare an increaſe in the ſame kind of iuſtification, and not a new kind of iuſtification. Now wheras the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> may ſeeme to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and oppoſe themſelues, the one prouing ſo often in his Epiſtles, that we are iuſtified by faith, without the workes<note place="margin">Rom. 4. 3. Galat. 3. 6.</note> of the Law: alledging the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> for iuſtification by faith, whom the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> here vſeth for iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by works. We muſt therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and ſcanne ſundry neceſſarie queſtions for the reconciling of them, as alſo for the remouing the aduerſary from off his blind ground in this weighty point.</p>
            <p>The firſt queſtion to be ſcanned is, what faith the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> meaneth or ſpeaketh of in this place, the which he maketh ſo inſufficient; whether hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, miraculous, hypocriticall, or liuely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3815:38"/> and operatiue. It is true that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of the laſt, as appeareth,<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 5. 6.</note> Galathians 5. 5. 6. <hi>Circumciſion auaileth nothing nor vncircumciſion, but faith which worketh by loue.</hi> But the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi>
               <note place="margin">No oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene the Apoſtles. I am. 2. 19. Great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a liuing faith and a dead faith.</note> ſpeaketh of the firſt, namely, hiſtoricall, as appeareth in the 19. verſe of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter; which he calleth the faith of diuels. So then they both ſpeake the truth, the one that we are iuſtified by faith onely without workes, ſpeaking of a liuely faith; the other, that we are not iuſtified by faith onely, ſpeaking of a dead barren, and counterfet faith.</p>
            <p>The ſecond queſtion to be ſcanned is, what iuſtification the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> meaneth; for there is a twofold iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as there are ſundry ſorts of faith. Firſt therefore we are iuſtified before God of which iuſtification the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, Pſa. 32. 1. 2. <hi>Bleſſed is that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 43. Pſal. 32. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>man vnto whom the Lord imputeth not his ſinne.</hi> Of which righteouſneſſe and iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, who ſaith, <hi>That Abraham beleeued, and it was</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground for iuſtifying faith.</note> 
               <hi>counted vnto him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iuſtification is before men, which we haue by workes, they being as eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3815:39"/> that we are righteous before God. Of this iuſtification doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeake: for <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering vp of his ſonne could not be the cauſe of his righteouſneſſe before God; for his<note place="margin">Rom. 4. 18.</note> faith in the promiſe was reckoned vnto him for righteouſneſſe thirty yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he offered vp his ſonne. Therefore before God was his faith not made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect through workes, but before men. Beſides, we reade of but few workes that the theefe on the croſſe wrought. Yet<note place="margin">Luke 23. 42. 43.</note> through faith was he iuſtified, and the heauenly paradiſe promiſed vnto him.</p>
            <p>The third queſtion to be ſcanned is, what works the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> meaneth, whether workes going before or after faith. It is certaine that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of workes going before faith, which he denieth to be able to iuſtifie vs, as appeareth, Galath. 5. 2. 3. 4. <hi>Behold I Paul ſay vnto you, that if ye be circumciſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 23. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing: for I teſtifie againe to euery man which is circumciſed that he is bound to keepe the whole Law. Ye are aboliſhed from Chriſt, whoſoeuer are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law, ye are fallen from grace.</hi> But Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of workes which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3815:39"/> follow faith, as appeareth in the 18. verſe,<note place="margin">Iames 2. 18. In nature cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of things go before their effects.</note> where he ſaith thus, <hi>Shew me thy faith out of thy workes, and I will ſhew thee my faith by my workes.</hi> Beſides, the author to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes declareth that <hi>Abrahams</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſacrifice was a worke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing faith, for he ſaith, <hi>That by faith</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 11. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham offered vp his ſonne Iſaacke.</hi> Workes then that follow Iuſtification cannot be the cauſes thereof; wherefore the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> muſt needs ſpeake of Iuſtification before men, and not before God.</p>
            <p>The fourth queſtion to be ſcanned, is touching the perſons with whom they haue to deale; a diſtinction is very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.<note place="margin">Rom. 103.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was to deale with phariſaicall hypocrites, and Iewiſh teachers, who held and taught, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they obſerued the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they could not be ſaued. But the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> was to deale with carnall libertines and Epicure-like profeſſours, who boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of a barren faith, and neglected to bring forth the fruits of righteouſneſſe. Many there were that vpon the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of faith, gaue libertie to the fleſh, and thereby became the ſeruants of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3815:40"/> as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 18. 19</note> therefore there muſt needs be neceſſitie of their ſeuerall doctrine, and no oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in it: the one being to deale with ſuch as too much preferred workes: the other being to deale with ſuch as too much neglected them. From whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples<note place="margin">People of different qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities muſt haue different doctrine preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</note> the Miniſters of the Goſpell may learne, that one kind of doctrine cannot be neceſſarie at all times, in all places, and to all perſons; therefore muſt they take heede to their flockes, wiſely and perfectly to guide by the rule of faith, in the life of life: for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>5</label> The fift vſe, is an admonition againſt ignorance. Our doctrine will not giue vs libertie nor licence to pleade for ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity;<note place="margin">Knowledge very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the life of faith. Chriſtians may make ſome vſe of Satan, for he knowes much and laboureth much. Pro. 8. 10. 11.</note> for where there is blindneſſe in the iudgement, there cannot be but ſin in the practiſe. Therefore ſearch we for knowledge as for hid treaſures; let vs make choiſe of wiſedome before gold, and preferre it before pearles. But for our better proceeding, conſider we of ſome motiues and ſpeciall inducements.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the neceſſitie of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Our grand enemy the Diuell is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3815:40"/> ſubtill, and well practiſed in our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold corruptions: yea he vnderſtandeth hiſtorically the Scriptures, he rageth in theſe laſt and worſt dayes: inſomuch, that although he cannot hinder many from profeſſion, yet he keepeth many from ſauing knowledge, driuing men into extreames, conceits, and baſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities. Pray we therefore earneſtly for a ſanctified vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Secondly, knowledge is the ground<note place="margin">Men that will beleeue God muſt know God. Ro. 10. 17. 18 19 Acts 8. 30. 37.</note> of faith; therefore little knowledge, little faith; no knowledge, no faith: for, <hi>How can we beleeue in him, of whom we haue not heard?</hi> When <hi>Philip</hi> had made knowne Chriſt vnto the Eunuch, <hi>he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and was baptized.</hi> Although there may be knowledge where there is not ſauing faith, yet there can neuer be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing faith without knowledge. He ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that would bring much glorie to God, muſt labour for much knowledge: both to be acquainted with the will of God, as alſo the wayes of ſin and deceits<note place="margin">He that wold forſake ſinne and Satan muſt learne to know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of corruption. He that would ouercome the enemy, muſt ſeeke to know what way the enemy cometh, and how he layeth his baites and ſnares. So there
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3815:41"/> can be no ouercomming of ſinne and Satan, vnleſſe we be acquainted with their ſtratagems.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a life without knowledge, is a life without faith; and a life without faith, is a life without God. Chriſt ſaith, that <hi>he knoweth his ſheepe, and is knowne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10. 14. Iohn 13. 17.</note> 
               <hi>of them:</hi> ſo then, no knowing of Chriſt, no ſheepe of Chriſts. <hi>If ye know theſe things</hi> (ſaith he to his Diſciples) <hi>bleſſed are ye if ye do them:</hi> as if he ſhould haue ſaid otherwiſe, If ye do not know theſe<note place="margin">Knowledge is part of gods image reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in his children.</note> things, ye can neuer do them. Would we then differ from Pagans and ſenſleſſe creatures, and withall, do the will of God? Let vs ſeeke for knowledge, for, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, good meanings will not ſerue the turne, the vaine truſtings of ignorant perſons, are both barbarous and dangerous. He that dependeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his good meaning, ſhall be guiltie<note place="margin">Good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings without good actions can neither pleaſe God, nor bring peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> both of ſinnes of commiſſion and omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. What ground then can ſuch haue of their ſaluation?</p>
            <p>Fiftly, no aſſurance nor ſound com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort without knowledge: for there can be no applying of the promiſes without
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3815:41"/> faith; and faith there cannot be without knowledge. The conſciences of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God wil oftentimes witneſſe the ſame; when they practiſe things they doubt of, what ioy or peace haue they? For when their faith cannot truly apply, their ſtay and comfort ceaſſeth, becauſe nothing ſooner bereaueth the child of<note place="margin">Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to do Gods will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will.</note> God of his comfort, then when he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that he hath not done Gods will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will. Therefore, for the attaining of this excellent grace, I will lay downe ſome ſpeciall meanes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, labour for an humbled and deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted<note place="margin">Meanes for the getting of knowledge.</note> ſpirit; for, <hi>The Lord will teach the humble his wayes, Pſal.</hi> 25. 9. Secondly, finde out thy wants by an able Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and lay them open before the Lord by earneſt prayer; for, <hi>The hungrie the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Lord filleth with good things, but the rich he ſendeth away empty.</hi> Thirdly, frequent the houſe of God, and the ſociety of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for, ſuch as do his will, are moſt like to know his will. Fourthly, be full of heauenly meditations, labour to ſerue the Lord in all thy actions. <hi>Dauid</hi> had got <hi>more wiſedome then his teachers</hi> by<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 99. 100.</note> this meanes. Fiftly, practiſe that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3815:42"/> which the Lord already hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon thee: examine how thou haſt applied euery Sabbath daies worke; For, no doubt, if thou liue vnder an able Miniſterie, thou mayſt be ſearching thy failings, either in thy generall or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular calling, or both. The reaſon why<note place="margin">He that wold know much muſt practiſe much.</note> men know little, is becauſe they practiſe little. The husbandman tilleth no more ground then he meaneth to ſowe; euen ſo men litle reſpect that which they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to do: it is ſinne therefore and diſobedience that keepeth men in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in theſe Sunne-ſhine dayes of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, remember the duty of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing,<note place="margin">Thankes for bleſſings are alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</note> both for thy knowledge, and for the meanes of knowledge; let it appeare that thou prizeſt it at an high rate by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the donor. The gift of a penny deſerueth thankes of him that is in need of it, therefore a great gift muſt needs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and require great thankes.</p>
            <p>Seuently impart thy gift to others; lay<note place="margin">He that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhal reape by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more then he ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> it not vp in a napkin. The mother that biddeth the child giue his brother ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that ſhe gaue him, if he do not, ſhe telleth him that ſhe will giue him no
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3815:42"/> more: euen ſo is it iuſt with God, that ſuch as haue bene churliſh and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent this way, ſhould not onely be kept without more, but likewiſe depriued of the comfort and benefit of that which they haue.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>6</label> The ſixt vſe may ſerue to encourage all true beleeuers to proceed and hold on in the workes of faith: for ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are in high eſteeme with the Lord; that faith which worketh by loue, is a bleſſed faith: vngrounded actions end in<note place="margin">Grounded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions well done ſhall haue a reward</note> miſery, but grounded actions cannot but end in comfort: For <hi>he is faithfull that hath promiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The remarkable notes of ſuch faithfull<note place="margin">Euangelicall workes are cheerefull ſound and conſtant.</note> workers are theſe; firſt, his ſeruice is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready ſeruice, for he loueth his God, and beleeueth the promiſes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is ordinarily ſound both for matter, manner, and end: but if there be a failing, there is ſorrow and repentance, when it is ſeene; as alſo a more ſtrict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of his actions for time to come. Thirdly, it is conſtant; the more faith the more fruite. For as he laboureth daily for knowledge, ſo both the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance &amp; increaſe thereof muſt needs
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3815:43"/> produce a conſtant &amp; enlarged practiſe. Thus as he laboureth for the weldoing of that which he doth, ſo his care is to do much; not onely for the anſwering of his gifts and graces receiued, but alſo for the accompliſhing of that vniuerſall obedience which is required of him; for <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3815:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
